Alright guys, congratulations on making it this far.
We are up to the last module of date print modules to
congratulations. So, this is all about gauging intensity and
respirator. Gauging intensity is simply
and knowing how hard someone's working that may sound silly,
but there's actually a lot to it. So gauging intensity,
the whole purpose is to make sure that the intensity that we want them
to be is matching where they're actually at.
And it's not always super clairvoyant or easy to tell why
intensity they're at. And make sure they're having an effective workout.
If it doesn't match, if there's a mismatch,
then the workout isn't effective. If we're pushing them too hard,
it's not effective. If we're not pushing hard enough,
it's not effective. It tells us the workouts of the client's capacity,
if we get really good at gauge their intensity,
then we can make sure we're meeting or slightly exceeding the capacity to
induce progress. And largely prevents over or under
training. We use the easy medium or
hard scale. Now you would have learned to potentially RKE 1 to 10.
What I need to remember is our thing about keeping
things basic. 1 to 10 is too many options
for a beginner. Easy, medium or hard makes it easier for them to make
a choice. So what we do during our workouts is simply ask,
hey John, after a set, was that easy?
Was that medium or was that hard?
If they say easy, it means that they did comfortably,
but they can do more reps. If they say medium,
it was challenging, but manageable. If they say hard,
it was near maximum effort. It's hard to keep going.
In terms of recovery and rest periods,
you want to simply ask, are you out of breath?
How out of breath are you? Being slightly out of breath is okay,
they're pushing hard, they're working hard.
Being very out of breath is not good because when you're really out of
breath it means that you stop the set because your out of breath,
your cardio has become a limiting factor rather than your muscle.
For example, if you do squats for a set of 30 plus,
you'll probably go to stop because is just so out of breath,
rather than your muscles not having any more in them.
Rest periods are obviously important, they allow muscle recovery,
it allows them to maintain their workout intensity and prevent injury.
Now while we do use breathlessness as our gauge of recovery,
there's not some guidelines, between sets 60 to 90 seconds is
good for most. We're working with beginners here,
so the typically on the shorter spectrum of that.
Extra point, men, women,
have different rest periods too, women,
because they typically have less muscle than men,
take less time to recover, because muscle uses oxygen,
and men have more oxygen, typically.
So a smaller female can do a set of squats to failure and do
another set maybe 45 seconds later,
whereas a larger man will take two to three minutes.
So it depends. Of course,
compound movements have longer wrist periods because using more muscular
chart, which means more oxygen as well.
All that matters is that you're adjusting the intensity based on the exercise,
the person and the feedback and the easiest way to ask for feedback is
to ask how they're feeling. Are you ready? Are you out of breath?
That's typically be like I'm good to go or give me a minute
They're actually quite good at knowing how much rest they need